Guide to the Matthew Noyes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Matthew Noyes papers
1788-1827
MS 377
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Forty-four manuscript sermons of Matthew Noyes, Yale 1785, who preached in various Connecticut churches.
Noyes, Matthew, 1764-1839
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Catherine Noyes Lee, 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Matthew Noyes, a son of Judge William Noyes, of Lyme, Connecticut, was born in that town about 1764. Two brothers were graduated here, in 1775 and 1781 respectively.
After graduation he studied theology with the Rev. Dr. Josiah Whitney (Yale 1752), of Brooklyn, Connecticut, and was licensed to preach by the Middlesex Association of Ministers on September 3, 1788.
In March, 1790, he began preaching in Northford Society in North Branford, Connecticut, and in May he was called to the pastorate, on a salary of 90 pounds. He accepted, and on August 18 he was ordained Pastor. The sermon on the occasion, by the Rev. Dr. Elizur Goodrich (Yale 1752), was afterwards published.
His labors as pastor were suspended in 1833, though his formal dismission was delayed until the installation of his successor on December 1, 1835. In this period of over forty-five years, there were two hundred and one additions to the members of the church.
He died in Northford on September 23, 1839, in his 76th year.
He was chosen a Fellow at Yale College in May, 1823, and continued in office until his death.
He was reputed to be among the richest ministers in Connecticut in his generation.
He married, on November 7, 1790, Mary, youngest daughter of the Rev. Stephen Johnson (Yale 1743), of Lyme, Connecticut, who died in Northford on September 1, 1851, aged 83 years. Their only child, a daughter, died in early womanhood.
(Taken from Yale Biographies and Annals, 1778-1792, Class of 1785, 433-34).
Scope and Contents
Forty-four manuscript sermons of Matthew Noyes, Yale 1785, who preached in various Connecticut churches.
Connecticut; Sermons; Clergy; Noyes, Matthew, 1764-1839; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1785
- Inventory
  - Genesis 22:12, 1799 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Genesis 22:14, 1813 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deuteronomy 8:2, 1815 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - I Kings 17:1, 1815 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - I Kings 20:32, 1803 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - II Chronicles 28:10, 1795 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Psalms 16:8, 1823 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Psalms 107:7, 1793 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Psalms 116:12, 1790 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Proverbs 14:34 (2 sermons), 1793 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Isaiah 42:8, 1819 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Isaiah 53:1, 1809 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jeremiah 2:37, 1803 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jeremiah 8:20, 1796 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jeremiah 14:12, 1800 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jeremiah 25:32, 1797 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hosea 4:3, 1812 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hosea 4:7, 1809 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Joel 2:15, 1822 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Amos 4:12, 1812 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Malachi 3:7, 1813 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Malachi 3:16, 1807 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Matthew 8:8-9, 1805 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Matthew 19:19, 1812 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Matthew 24:12, 1788 June (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Luke 5:31, 1794 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Luke 13:4-5, 1793 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Luke 13:24, 1821 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Luke 15:20-21, 1827 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - John 2:17, 1811 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - John 15:1-2, 1821 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - John 6:47, 1810 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Romans 13:7-9, 1798 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - I Corinthians 2:7, 1794 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - II Corinthians 5:1, 1805 August 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Galatians 3:10, 1803 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - I Thessalonians 1:5, 1809 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - I Thessalonians 4:11, 1805 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hebrews 12:14, 1820 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - James 4:10, 1810 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 1 John 3:8, 1806 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Revelations 3:20, 1790 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Revelations 12:7-8, 1801 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 43)